<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anti-Goliah: or An epistle to Mr. Brevint, containing some reflections upon his Saul, and Samuel, at Endor. / Written by E.W.</title>
            <author>Warner, John, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10269</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80925351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W904B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80925351</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80925351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2901:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anti-Goliah: or An epistle to Mr. Brevint, containing some reflections upon his Saul, and Samuel, at Endor. / Written by E.W.</title>
                  <author>Warner, John, 1628-1692.</author>
                  <author>E. W. (Edward Worsley), 1605-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>With leave of superiors.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Warner by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brevint, Daniel, 1616-1695. --  Saul and Samuel at Endor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANTI-GOLIAH: OR An Epiſtle to Mr. BREVINT, CONTAINING Some REFLECTIONS upon His SAUL, and SAMUEL, At ENDOR.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By E. W.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olunt videri aliquid dicere, dum tacere erubeſcunt, &amp; inania dicere non erubeſcunt.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
               <p>They would ſeeme to ſay ſomething, being ashamed to be ſilent, &amp; not ashamed to ſpeake Idly.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>With leave of Superiors, 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>House of Hanover bookplate</figDesc>
                  <p>MVNIFICENTIA REGIA. 1715.</p>
                  <p>GEORGIVS D. G. MAG. BR. FR. ET HIB. REX F. D.</p>
                  <byline>J. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Sculp</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou are invited to be not only <hi>Spectator;</hi> but <hi>Judge</hi> of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat, betwixt a Gyant, &amp; a Pigmy, a Philiſtin, &amp; an Iſraelit, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> &amp; one of the army of the Living God. Our forces are unequall; he <hi>a man of war, from his youth,</hi> trained up to ſuch battles; I <hi>but a youth,</hi> a raw ſouldier in them: he an ancient <hi>Doctor</hi> of Divinity; &amp; I a y oung Divine, ſcarce worthy of that name. Another advantage he hath, by living amongſt us, as he ſayth in his preface, <hi>17.</hi> yeares, By which meanes, if there be any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortifyed weake part in our Camp, any fault in our Armour whither defenſive, or offenſive, it cannot have eſcaped his obſerving eye. where as I have ſcarce any other proſpect of their Camp, or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, then what he, &amp; his Brethren, his fellow ſouldiers in this warfare, are
<pb facs="tcp:192171:3"/>pleaſed to give of them: Laſtly he hath often beene in ſuch engagements; &amp; this is the firſt time that ever I entred the liſts in this nature. Yet I hope in God the Protector of the Innocent: who is pleaſed to <hi>make uſe of weake things to confound the things, which are myghty, &amp; the foolish things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe: that no flesh should glory in his Preſence. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi> The goodneſſe of my Cauſe is likewiſe a greate encouragement, ſeing I am to fyght for <hi>Truth, nay Revealed, &amp; Divine Truth:</hi> which will at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail One only favour I deſire of you, Chriſtian Reader, that if in any place you find me foyled, (of which I am not conſcious) what you find amiſſe, you charge on my weakeneſſe: when you ſee I foyle my adverſary, you attribute th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> victory to that <hi>Truth,</hi> which I fyght for which gives me ſtrength &amp; courage: &amp; that you Acknowledge, &amp; Profeſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192171:3"/>
            <head>ANTI-GOLIAH: OR An Epiſtle to Mr. BREVINT, CONTAINING Some REFLECTIONS upon His SAUL, and SAMUEL At ENDOR.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> My intent and reaſon of the Title.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Cauſe</hi> for which I plead, is the <hi>Innocency</hi> of the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,</hi> wrongfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of heinous Crimes: The <hi>concern</hi> I have in this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> is my <hi>Duty</hi> to a <hi>Pious Indulgent Mother,</hi> odiouſly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192171:4"/>traduced with virulent Calumnies: My <hi>End,</hi> is to wipe off her Face the Dirt you caſt on it: The <hi>means</hi> I uſe to attain this End, is <hi>ſincerity</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating what She believes, and rejecting what is untruly, and by conſequence, unjuſtly charged on Her: You, Sir, are the <hi>Plaintiff,</hi> I the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant,</hi> and the <hi>Reader,</hi> our <hi>Iudge.</hi> My <hi>Hope</hi> is not in ſtrength of Wit or Learning, in which I will not contend with you; but in the <hi>juſtice</hi> of my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>equity</hi> of my <hi>Iudge,</hi> and above all, in the <hi>help</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the Protector of the Innocent: who as he promis'd to aſſiſt his <hi>Church to the end of the world,</hi> will not be wanting to thoſe, who defend her. Your quality of <hi>Plaintiff</hi> obliges you to prove, what you charge on us; and unleſs your proofs be convincing, they are inſignificant, our bare denial acquits us: For <hi>In doubtful Caſes, the Defendant ought to be favoured rather than the Plaintiff.</hi> And, <hi>Each one is to be thought good, till he be proved naught.</hi> Which are two Rules of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law, ſo conformable to Natural Reaſon, that they need no proof to confirm them.</p>
               <p>Your Title is, <hi>Saul and Samuel, at Endor.</hi> Very myſterious! But what you mean, who can tell? The Hiſtory you allude to, is known to every body; <hi>Saul,</hi> a lawful, but unfortunate King, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a dangerous war, ſtrongly attacked by his enemies, weakly aſſiſted by his ſubjects, and (which is worſt of all) abandoned of God; had recourſe to <hi>Samuel,</hi> in the beſt, and it may be, the onely manner, he thought on, to know
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192171:4"/>his Fate from that Oracle, which had given him the firſt Tydings of his Kingdom. With this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he goes to <hi>Endor.</hi> This is the Hiſtory. But what is this to our preſent Times or Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies? Who is the <hi>Saul</hi> you mean? Who is <hi>Samuel?</hi> Where is <hi>Endor?</hi> What War? If we conſider the date of your Book, we may gueſs, that is was compoſed aboud the time of the <hi>Holland</hi> War 1672. or 1673. I dare not ſay you mean that, for the Honour due to Perſons concerned. But tell what you mean, and apply your perſons to our purpoſe, or acknowledge your Title to be nothing to the purpoſe. Until you explicate your meaning, we will admit, what you give us: We will not refuſe <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Samuel:</hi> Whereof the one was a <hi>true Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> and both died in Communion of the True Church: both were ſound in <hi>Faith;</hi> although one of them for diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying God's Commands, and <hi>not hoping in God,</hi> deſervedly loſt his Kingdom, and probably his Soul too. So he may be a Type of ſuch <hi>Catholicks,</hi> who entirely believe all which God revealed, but live not according to their Belief: <hi>&amp; Samuel</hi> is a Type of thoſe whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> is animated with <hi>Charity,</hi> and both are Friutful of good Works. But ſeeing you perſonate us under thoſe names; be pleaſed to give us leave to repreſent you by the Name of <hi>Goliah:</hi> for <hi>Goliah</hi> was in a party co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that Church they were of, ſo are you in one contrary to ours: He was a profeſt Enemy to <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſo are you to us: He chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192171:5"/>all the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> ſo do you all us: He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached them, for not accepting that Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, ſo do you us, with not incountring your Books: your inſulting Language shews you to be animated with a Spirit of Vanity, of Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, of too great eſteem of your own Abilities, and Contempt of others, not unlike that which appeared in <hi>Goliah.</hi> Infine, To accomplish the Paralel, we shall find you alledging reaſons, which deſtroy your own Cauſe; as <hi>Goliah</hi> brought a ſword to cut off his own Head.</p>
               <p>For theſe reaſons I call this Pamphlet <hi>Anti-Goliah.</hi> I do not preſume to take to my ſelf the Name of <hi>David,</hi> who was the Champion of God: There were others who bore Armes in that War againſt <hi>Goliah</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtins;</hi> and their quality ſatisfies me,</p>
               <p>You add in Title, <hi>The new ways of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Service, which uſually tempt men to Rome.</hi> Thoſe you mention are indeed <hi>New ways</hi> to incite Men to <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo <hi>New,</hi> that I am perſwaded no catholick ever hearde of them, but from your Book. I know no other exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ways to convert Men to <hi>Rome,</hi> but the <hi>Motives of Credibility,</hi> which are briefly related by St. <hi>Auſtin. l. Cont. Epiſt. Fundam. c.</hi> 4. and more largely by <hi>Bellar. Leſſius, &amp; Divines, Tract. de Fide,</hi> viz. the <hi>Vnity, Sanctity, Excellency of Faith,</hi> its Propagation in ſo short a time, and the manner of it, its effects which followed it. The perpetual ſucceſſion of lawful Paſtors from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192171:5"/>the Apoſtles, till our days. The Teſtimony of Martyrs by their Blood, and of God by his Works, which are Miracles: The conſent of Nations, the Fulfilling of the Propheſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Infine, the very name of <hi>Catholick,</hi> which mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre all pretences of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, This Church only retains, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> writes it did in his time, and we ſee it doth in ours. Theſe are the Motives alleadged to invite Men to enter into the Communion of that Church, in which they are found, and of which they are verified. But I never heard any diſcourſe thus: <hi>Be of the Communion of the Roman Church, becauſe it adores two Chriſts</hi> (as you ſay c. 1.) <hi>giveth the ſcapular of S. Simon Stock</hi> (as c. 13.) <hi>ſays the beads of S. Dominick</hi> (c. 14.) <hi>uſes conſecrated Images</hi> (c. 16.) If you know any who uſe ſuch induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, name them: If you can name none, ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledge that your Book in its fore-head bears a great <hi>Calumny,</hi> an <hi>unexcuſable untruth:</hi> This is an <hi>Omen,</hi> of what <hi>ſincerity</hi> we are to expect in your whole Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>In your Preface, <hi>Not to be my own witneſs,</hi> ſay you; <hi>I make the caſe of Papiſts ſuch as I find it in their own Authors.</hi> It is harde meaſure when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſlip of a private pen, is charged on the whole Church, which often diſlikes, and ſometimes condemns it; yet had you kept to this Rule, you had been leſs blame worthy. I shall have occaſion, more than once, to mind you of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192171:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Your General Account of New Ways.</head>
               <p>PAge 1. <hi>What the Church of Chriſt hath ſingle, that of</hi> Rome <hi>hath double, the eternal God, and à mortal woman, two ſorts of Chriſts, two ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, two Mediators, two different wayes to obtain pardon of ſins, two Ladders to get up to Heaven, two ſorts of ſpiritual kindred, two Heads of the Church, and two different and ſometimes contrary words of God.</hi> When you writ this, ſure you had been in good company, and thence, <hi>geminis ſurgebat menſa lucernis:</hi> All things ſeemed double. It was well for us, that at that time, <hi>Hell, Heaven, Purgatory, Pope, the ſoul of Man, the Perſon of Chriſt, and the Nature of God,</hi> did not occur to you, otherwiſe you would have enlarged our Accuſation, and ſaid we believe <hi>two Popes, two ſouls of men, two Hells, two Heavens, two Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, two Perſons of Chriſt, two Divine Natures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is an accuſation of as heinous a nature as any can be: On What is it grounded? Whoſe Teſtimony is produced to prove it? See the Text, ſee the Margine, not one ſingle man named. Have you ſo ſoon forgotten your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Not to be your own witneſs; but to cite our Authors?</hi> We will uſe the right of <hi>Defendants,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:192171:6"/>and to a groundleſs falſe accuſation, return a flat denial oft its Truth. And, when you pleaſe, we will shew you, That we believe onely <hi>One God, one Chriſt, one way to obtain Pardon of Sins, the Mercy of God, one Way to Heaven, the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How the Church can be <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Catholick?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PAge 8. <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſay you, <hi>are well pleaſed with calling themſelves Catholicks.</hi> We are ſo; and ſo were Catholicks in S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s time, as we ſee <hi>l. cont. Epiſt. Fund.</hi> c. 4. That being one of the greateſt Motives of retaining him, <hi>S. Austin,</hi> in the Church. Hereticks both then, and now, would arrogate to their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that Title; yet could never compaſs it. No great wonder we should glory in that Name, ſeeing, as you ſay, <hi>Catholick Doctrine and Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, is the moſt eſſential Iewel, and the Soul of True Churches.</hi> You cannot give ſo great Praiſes to <hi>Catholick Doctrine</hi> (which is <hi>Faith</hi>) taken of it ſelf, but it will deſerve greater. Yet if compared with <hi>Charity,</hi> it muſt yield place; as you ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. But becauſe the matter is of conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and not rigthly underſtood by you, I will enlarge a little upon it.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:192171:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is an error as great as it is common, to think, that <hi>Faith in Chriſt</hi> (which is <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi>) began with the preaching of the Apoſtles, or of Chriſt himſelf: that Faith being as ancient almoſt as the world. For no ſooner had <hi>Adam,</hi> by breaking the Commandment, contracted the guilt of temporal and eternal Death to himſelf and all his poſterity, but God the Father decreed to ſend his only begotten Son, <hi>to blot out the hand-writing of the Decree which was againſt us;</hi> Col. 2.14. and to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile us again by that blood, which was to be shed for us. And revealing that Decree to man, raiſed him to hope for pardon by the merits of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> a <hi>Mediator,</hi> who was then promis'd, in whom he was commanded to <hi>believe,</hi> and from whom he was to expect his Redemption. From that moment we may date the beginning <hi>of Faith in Chriſt:</hi> although the Name he was to bear, was not then known, nor the time when he should come, nor the place where, nor the Family of which he was to be born. And all thoſe perſons who lived well, and were ſaved, either during the Law of Nature, or under the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law, <hi>Abraham, Iob, Iſaac, Iacob, Moyſes, David, Hieremy,</hi> &amp;c. as well as we, <hi>received of his fulneſſ,</hi> and were <hi>cleanſed in the blood of the Lamb;</hi> who for that reaſon, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 15.8. is ſaid to be <hi>ſlain from the beginning of the world,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ep. 157. <hi>Eadem Fides eſt, &amp; noſtra, &amp; illorum ......... Our Faith, is the ſame with that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192171:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Saints before Chriſt; for they believed that to come, which we believe paſt.</hi> And he proves it out of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. where having ſpoken of the faith of the Iſraelitical Miniſters, he adds, <hi>We having the ſame ſpirit of faith;</hi> that is believing the ſame things. And Tract. 45. in Joan. <hi>Temporavariata ſunt; non ſides ........ Times are altered, not Faith; the ſound of words is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, He is to come,</hi> and <hi>He is come; but the ſame faith united both thoſe who believed him to come, and thoſe who believe that he is come.</hi> Epiph. l. 1. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Haereſes, <hi>The ſame faith which now is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Holy Catholick Church, was</hi> before Chriſt <hi>in vigor.</hi> Hence <hi>Iuſtinus M. Apol</hi> 2. <hi>Euſebius l.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſt. c.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Demonſ. Evang. c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. ſay, there were Chriſtians long before Chriſt. Thus all faithful believers both before and after Chriſt, make up one Myſtical Body, whereof Chriſt is the Head.</p>
               <p>Two difficulties againſt this Doctrine occur, whoſe Explication will clear the miſt, which Mr. <hi>B.</hi> caſts before his Readers Eyes. The firſt, <hi>Epheſ. 3.5. S. Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>The myſtery of Chriſt was not made known in other ages to the ſons of men, as it is now revealed unto his Holy Apostles.</hi> The ſecond, We have another Prieſthood, another Altar another Sacrifice, other Rites, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo</hi> another Religion.</p>
               <p>I anſwer to the firſt, The different manner of announcing Chriſt, makes no change in Chriſt himſelf: as the different manner of explicating a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192171:8"/>Mathematical Demonſtration, alters not the Demonſtration, or thing demonſtrated. The Scripture is the ſame when cleerly and when obſcurely underſtood; and Faith is the ſame when it is more and more explicated, provided it change not its object, It may be ſaid to alter its ſtate, when its object is altered in quality; but it remains the ſame in ſubſtance, as long as its material and formal object ſubſiſts. Thus the ſame perſon, when <hi>Minor,</hi> is undera <hi>Tutor;</hi> from whoſe power he is exempted, when <hi>Major.</hi> Now the <hi>Law was our Tutor,</hi> Gal. 3. under which we were kept till by the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Faith was revealed, id eſt,</hi> explicated more cleerly.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond difficulty, <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> anſwers ep. 49. <hi>Diſpertita divinis eloquiis ſacrificia, ..... By the Divine Spirit ſacrifices were appointed, proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the times, that ſome should be offered before the New Teſtament was revealed... and ſame other now ſince its revelation ...... For as one and the ſame man, offering to God one thing in the morning, and another in the evening, cannot for that be ſaid to change God or his Religion, ſo in ſeveral Ages, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome things were offered anciently, others at preſent, yet we have neither changed God, nor our Religion.</hi> Thus <hi>S. Auſtin.</hi> Which Doctrine well applied, will cleer all you ſay in this Chapter.</p>
               <p>Page 8. You ſay, <hi>The firſt Title the faithful had after the Aſcenſion, was to be called Chriſtians.</hi> The thing was long before, even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. I wish you had proved that name to be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192171:8"/>the <hi>firſt Title</hi> after the Aſcenſion; for I think it certain, they had another name before that. The name <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was firſt known at <hi>Antioch, Act. 11.26.</hi> which was many years after the Aſcenſion, as is gathered out of the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> for it was after the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> his retreat into <hi>Arabia,</hi> his return to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> his Journey to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> three years after that; and then at his excurſion into <hi>Syria,</hi> and preaching at <hi>Antioch,</hi> that name was taken up Is it credible, that a Congregation of men should be ſo long together, and have no name to be known by? This might ſuffice, though no name had been left on record, as there is one, <hi>Act. 6.1.2.7.</hi> where the faithful are three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times called <hi>Diſciples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 9 <hi>No Philoſophers were ever able with all their wit, to extend their opinions beyond their Schools nor the greateſt Kings ſettle their Laws, beyond their Dominions;</hi> ſay you very falſly: for <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Carteſius</hi> divide all the Philoſophers of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which neither ever had a School. And <hi>Iustinian</hi>'s Laws are ſettled in <hi>Spain,</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> and for ſome Caſes in <hi>England,</hi> where his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me was ſcarce know during his life. See, Sir, how dangerous it is to follow your fancy! But let us admit what you ſay, and we shall find you <hi>Goliah</hi>-like armed with a ſword to cut off your own head; not to hurt your enemy. What ſay you, <hi>Hereticks cannot ſpread their errors much beyond their own abode: God alone, can create a new light,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192171:9"/>which shall ſpread a bright day over the world.</hi> Where you condemn your own Reformation, which is ſcarce known out of the <hi>British Iles;</hi> and make a Panegyrick of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> which is ſpread over the world, and fills the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> with the light of the Goſpel; which, as you ſay, <hi>God alone can do.</hi> Truth extorts this teſtimony from your pen. God grant you grace to profeſs with ſincerity of heart, what you unwittingly ſaid with your mouth.</p>
               <p>Page 11. <hi>Many wiſe men take Roman Catholick for a Bull.</hi> The Planets have their Ecclipſes, the Sun it ſelf his ſpots, and the wiſeſt men their follies. Such is childish quibbling upon words in ſerious grave matters. But why is it <hi>a Bull?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, <hi>Catholick</hi> ſignifies <hi>Vniverſal,</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> imports ſomething <hi>particular.</hi> Do thoſe <hi>wiſe men,</hi> think it a <hi>Bull,</hi> to call the Catholick Church, <hi>Apostolick,</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were <hi>ſingular men,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was but one man? Aud if we may call the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick;</hi> without being cenſured for incongruity of ſpeech (though thoſe names be taken from ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) why not <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> although that name be taken from one place? Such a Church hath more of univerſality than any ſingle perſon.</p>
               <p>God forbid I should make compariſons bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt Chriſt and the Roman Church, which adores him as her God. I intend no more here,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192171:9"/>than to shew by this undeniable inſtance, that a denomination taken from à particular body, thing, or perſon, may be given to a univerſal Congregation. So thoſe <hi>wiſe men</hi> are much out in this cenſure.</p>
               <p>But why is the Church denominated from <hi>Rome,</hi> rather than from any other place? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe as the <hi>Poliglott</hi> acknowledges, <hi>Prolog.</hi> 10. It was alwayes held to be <hi>the Principal Church,</hi> and <hi>moſt constantly adhered to ancient Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi> Becauſe it preſides over the reſt, as the Head over the Body, ſays the ſecond General Council to <hi>Damaſus.</hi> Becauſe in it S. <hi>Peter</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided, who received the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, was the Rock on which the Church is built, is the foundation of Jurisdiction, and the Center of Eccleſiaſtical Unity.</p>
               <p>Page 22. <hi>If the Pope be the Roman Church's Head, Maſſe is its Body.</hi> Very witty! Here is a new way to unchurch all Papiſts, who can be no part of the Roman Church, which contains the Pope, as Head, and Maſs, as Body: and we are neither Pope, nor Maſs. I am perſwaded wiſe men will pity your labours, ſo ill ſpent in ſtudies, ſeeing after all you cannot diſtinguish betwixt a Church, and her Religious Service, or <hi>Lyturgy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibidem, Enquire of all the Fathers, when and where they,</hi> the Apoſtles <hi>ſung Maſs publickly.</hi> A ſearch worhy of your ſelf, to ſeek whether they ſung Maſs in Market-places, when their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192171:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Meetings <hi>were Antelucanis horis,</hi> ſays <hi>Pliny.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Chriſtians, to ſave their Lives, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to <hi>wander in deſerts, and mountains, and dens, and caves of the earth,</hi> Heb. 11.38.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. <hi>Purgatory, that Subterranean Rome:</hi> Rome <hi>ſends down Maſſes to that; that helps</hi> Rome <hi>with wealth, honours, and riches.</hi> The Primitive Chriſtians had Maſs for the Dead, as well as <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may ſee in S. <hi>Auſtin l. de cura pro mortuis c. 1. &amp; Enchir. c. 110.</hi> in this later place, he ſays. <hi>Neque negandum eſt. It ought not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that the deceaſed ſouls are eaſed by the piety of their ſurviving friends, when the ſacrifice of the Mediator is offered for them, or Alms given in the Church. That theſe things eaſe thoſe ſouls, who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the courſe of this life, lived ſo as to merit it. For there is a manner of life, neither ſoo good, as not to need thoſe helps, nor ſo bad, as to receive no benefit by them. And there is another ſo good, as not to need them; and a third ſo bad, as to be incapable of eaſe even by them.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee in theſe words, 1. <hi>Maſs, Sacrificium Mediatoris: The ſacrifice of our Mediator.</hi> You ſee 2. Maſs for the Dead; <hi>Pro illis offertur: It is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up for them.</hi> You ſee 3. Alms given in the Church for them. <hi>Pro illis Eleemoſynae in Eccleſia fiunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee 4. Purgatory, Hell, and Heaven, three diſtinct ſtates of faithful ſouls departed. Thoſe ſoo good, as not to need help, are in <hi>Heaven:</hi> thoſe ſo bad as not to be capable of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192171:10"/>eaſe by ſuffrages, are in <hi>Hell:</hi> Thoſe ſo bad as to need them, and ſo good, as to receive eaſe by them, are in <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take notice, That the Saint here doth not ſpeak as of a doubtful matter, or on his private opinion, of what may be done; but as of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable truth and a common practice of the Church. So what you reproach to <hi>Rome,</hi> was the practice of the pureſt times.</p>
               <p>And as for the ſubſtance of Maſs, you find it alſo in S. <hi>Auſtin ep. 49. q. 3.</hi> where he ſpeaks of a ſacrifice in <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thoſe of the Synagogue. This ſacrifice was inſtituted and commanded by our B. Saviour in his laſt Supper, and no doubt but the Apoſtles obeyed that command. Therefore they ſaid Maſs.</p>
               <p>If theſe clear convincing Proofs of thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and capital Myſteries of our Religion, do not prove that <hi>Popery</hi> was from the beginning, tell us when it began?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 333. You ſay, <hi>The ninth Century, the worſt, the ſaddeſt, and the ignoranteſt Age of the Church, drowned the Goſpel with Popery, and began in good earneſt to ſet up the</hi> Abominable deſolation <hi>in the Roman Church.</hi> So that there you aſſure us, that, till then there was no Popery, ſeeing that then it <hi>began to be ſet up.</hi> Yet ſee how inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent your aſſertions are. <hi>P.</hi> 105. and 340. you make <hi>S. Iohn Damaſc.</hi> a Papiſt, who lived in the Eighth Age. <hi>P.</hi> 46. you make <hi>S. Gregory</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192171:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Great and <hi>S. Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tours</hi> Papiſts, who lived in the beginning of the Seventh Age and later end of the Sixth. <hi>P.</hi> 95 you make <hi>S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> declaim againſt papiſts; there were then Papiſts in the Fifth Age. <hi>P.</hi> 149. the building of <hi>S. Mary Majors</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Liberius</hi> his time (who lived in the Fourth Age) is charged on Papiſts. <hi>P.</hi> 328. Papiſts are charged for uſing Oyle to cure Diſeaſes, which was uſed for that intent in the firſt Century by the Apoſtles themſelves; <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.13. <hi>They anointed with oyl many that were ſick, and healed them.</hi> So the Apoſtles were Papiſts, and Popery was extant even in the Firſt Age; and this by your Confeſſion. Conſider hereafter a little better what you write, if not for Truth's ſake (which you ſeem to regard very little) at leaſt for your own reputation, which cannot but ſink very low, when ſuch palpable Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictions are diſcovered in your Writings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Miracles and Viſions.</head>
               <p>MIracles alwayes are effects, which ſurpaſs the force of Nature, whether it be for the ſubſtance of the work, as the raiſing of <hi>Lazarus, Iohn.</hi> 11. who had been four daves buried; or for the manner of it, as health reſtored to <hi>S. Peteer's</hi> Mother-in-Law; on a ſudden, without Phyſick,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192171:11"/>to ſuch ſtrength, as to be able immediately to ſerve them; <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.31. This was a <hi>Miracle,</hi> becauſe although it may be, she might have naturally recovered, yet that she should recover in an inſtant, is impoſſible to Nature or ſecunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cauſes.</p>
               <p>The Magicians had therefore reaſon to ſay, <hi>Digitus Dei eſt hic. This is God's Finger;</hi> Exod. 8.19. Whether they found that the force of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could not reach the production of thoſe flies or that Nature's Activity (when applied by the Magicians) was ſuſpended by God: which are two manners of Working Miracles. For it is as miraculous to ſuſpend the Action of Nature, when Agents are applied to Subjects duly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; as to raiſe it to produce, what of it ſelf it cannot. Miraculous was the preſervation of Three Children in the Furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. as well as the opening of a Rock with the ſtroke of a Rod, to give Waters, <hi>Num.</hi> 20. yet in a diffe-manner, one by breaking the Action of Fire, the other by giving grearer ſtrength to that ſtroke, than that of Cannon-Bullets.</p>
               <p>The end of Miracles, is not only to declare God's infinite Power and Dominion over all Creatures, which by Natural Reaſon, without Miracles is ſufficiently known: nor always the ſole eaſing of a perſon in diſtreſs; although this is ſometimes the Motive, as when Oyl was mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, to relieve the poor Widdow: and very frequently in the Deſert. They are moreover
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192171:12"/>Declarations of Gods mind unto us, and a kind of <hi>Language of God,</hi> ſo peculiar to himſelf, that although every body underſtands it, yet no Man, no Angel can ſpeak it for want of its only Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, God's Omnipotency. <hi>Men ſpeak by words,</hi> ſays <hi>S. Auſtin ep. 49. q. 6. God by Actions. Divina potentia etiam factis loquitur.</hi> And before him <hi>Origen l. 2. cont. Celſum, Chriſt our Lord not only tanght with his words, but alſo with his works</hi> By theſe <hi>God confirmed the Word,</hi> or Preaching, <hi>of the Apoſtles,</hi> Mar. <hi>ult. &amp;</hi> Heb. <hi>2.4.</hi> He is ſaid <hi>to have born witneſs, with ſigns and wonders, and divers miracles and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Hence it is, that Miracles ary by ſome Fathers called <hi>the Seal God,</hi> which compariſon you uſe <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 34. All Chriſtian Miracles are ...... for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, and authorizing true Chriſtian and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Truth amongſt Infidels.</hi> That many have been made for that end; I grant; but that none are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de but for that end, you ſay it, but can never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve it, becauſe it is not true. For the budding of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, <hi>Num. 17.</hi> was to confirm to him and his poſterity, the Prieſts Office. The Dew on <hi>Gedeon</hi>'s Furre, <hi>Iud.</hi> 6.6. was to encourage him againſt the Madianites <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Force was to humble the Philiſtins, and protect the Iſraelites. That Salt thrown into a Fountain, should change the nature of its Waters, <hi>4. Reg. 2.</hi> was for the comfort of the Neighbours. The vertue of the Waters cauſing a Curſe, <hi>Num 5.</hi> was to eaſe the Husband of his Jealouſie; which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192171:12"/>vertue was doubtleſs miraculous ſeeing all the Prieſt did to them, could not ſo much alter their nature, as to give them a putrifying quality. Or if it could, yet ſuch an inanimate Creature could never diſtinguish betwixt the Guilty and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, ſo as to do no hurt to the guiltleſs, and rot the guilty. Several others occur in Scripture and elſewhere, made for other private ends, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in confirmation of ſome Vertue, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for even Temporal ends. The Veſtal car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying water in a Sive, or leading a Ship with her Girdle againſt the ſtream, was in confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Innocency. That Vertue in our Kings to cure a Diſeaſe, either in teſtimony of the Vertue of <hi>S. Edward,</hi> from whoſe time they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, or to shew that Regal Power is from God; or for other ends unknown to us. Out of theſe Examples it appears, that your aſſertion, that, <hi>All Miracles are wrought for confirmation of Faith amongſt Infidels,</hi> is untrue, and undefenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. One great fault is obſervable in your whole writing, ſome particular inſtances occurring to you, you preſently frame out of them general Axioms; which precipitated Judgments are often very erroneous. We have ſeen one Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of it; here follow others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 38.39.40. <hi>God,</hi> ſay you, <hi>proceeds in the New Law, as he did in the Old: In the beginning of both he doth undeniable wonders, and restrains the Devil and his Miniſters from doing any. After a time, when each Law was eſtablisht, God ceaſes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192171:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>from working Miracles, and the Devil is let looſe to act as he pleaſes.</hi> Thus you. That God acted in both Laws in ſome manner alike, confirming both with Miracles, is very true: But that the Devil was reſtrained and tied up from acting, at the beginning of either; or that God ceaſed from them in both, after ſome time, is moſt falſe.</p>
               <p>It is falſe, that the Devil was reſtrained from acting things, which to men ſeemed miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; for in the beginning of the Old Law, the Magicians for ſome time contended with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and did things like his Miracles; <hi>Exod. 7.</hi> And immediately after the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Tyanaeus</hi> is an inſtance, that the Devil had then as much liberty as ever, for there ſcarce ever was any Magician, who equalled him in ſeeming wonders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſay you, <hi>Oracles were ſuppreſt,</hi> Elimas <hi>ſtruck blind, Demoniacks ſilenced,</hi> Simon Magus <hi>beat down by S.</hi> Peter. What then? <hi>Ergo, the Devil was tied from all falſe Miracles Pag.</hi> 39. Thus you draw a general concluſion out of ſome particular inſtances, although there are others as evident for the contrary, as thoſe of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Adrian,</hi> of whom you your ſelf ſpeak; <hi>Pag.</hi> 36. prove there were ſeeming wonders wrought at that time, and we find in <hi>S. Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Theodoret l.</hi> 3. <hi>Hiſt. cap.</hi> 16. a pratling Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> near <hi>Antioch,</hi> whoſe mouth was ſtopt by <hi>S. Babilas</hi> his bones.</p>
               <p>It is alſo falſe, That Miracles ceaſed, when
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192171:13"/>the Old Law was eſtablisht; for the vertue of the Curſed Waters, <hi>Num.</hi> 5. continued to the end; that of the Sheep Pond, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. alſo; which two are recorded in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: As alſo thoſe of <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Elizeus</hi> in the 3. and 4. of <hi>Kings.</hi> The Old Law was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisht when <hi>Hieroboam</hi> ſet ut his Calfes, yet 3. <hi>Kings</hi> 13. three Miracles were wrought to confound that beginning Idolatry, and crush the Infant Schiſme in its Cradle. I ſay nothing of ſeveral other Miracles, not recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which yet are mentioned in other Fathers, to have continued to Chriſt his time; <hi>viz.</hi> that no fly should be found in the Temple, nor any noiſome ſmells, notwithſtanding ſo many Burnt Offerings: that the Wind should not blow away the Ashes of the Altar, which ſtood in an Open Court; that no Enemy should infeſt their Countrey, whilſt they went thrice a year to <hi>Hieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> which were continued till Chriſt's death, and that of the Synagogue. When you have conſidered theſe things, you will ſay that your aſſertion <hi>of Miracles ceaſing, when the Law was ſetled,</hi> was very rash.</p>
               <p>Seeing then, that God (as you ſay) proceeds in both Laws alike, Miracles having not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Old Law till the Death of Chriſt, and the end of the Law, they are not to cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in the New. But, ſay you, God ceaſed from Miracles, when there <hi>were Chriſtian Princes, to whoſe care he committed</hi> the Church, as willing to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192171:14"/>eaſe himſelf of the trouble; being tired with the labour. But your ſword will here do us ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice again: for <hi>p.</hi> 44. you acknowledge the Miracles by the Relicks of S. <hi>Stephen in Africa, and</hi> S. <hi>Gervaſius,</hi> and <hi>Protaſius</hi> at <hi>Milan,</hi> which being done in S. <hi>Auſtin's</hi> time, you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Miracles long after <hi>Chriſtian Princes were Nurſes</hi> of the Church. Such a perpetual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat there is in your Writings, and will be, while fancy fights againſt Truth, in one of a weak memory.</p>
               <p>Another Contradiction I find <hi>p.</hi> 37. where to shew your admirable Erudition, you ſay, that the Primitive Ermits <hi>retired to Deſerts to convert the Barbarous Inhabitants.</hi> Very rare! the world hath been hitherto in a great error, all univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally believing, that Ermits went to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, not to ſeek, but to flie all men; and it is evident, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> and ſeveral others, paſt a long age of moſt men, without ſeeing any man at all; which is ſo evident, that you could not but ſay and own it in this very place. <hi>Deſerts,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the refuge of Primitive Chriſtians from the face of their enemies:</hi> They went then to the Deſerts, to flie from their enemies; not to ſeek them there. So incoherent are your fancies, you ſay and unſay the ſame thing within ſix lines; let me adviſe you not to relie on every fancy, which preſents it ſelf; otherwiſe, it may be the ignorant may admire you, but certainly the learned will laugh at you. We have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192171:14"/>your Aſſertions, we will now hear your Proofs.</p>
               <p>Pag. 37. <hi>The World being ſufficiently called to the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the Holy Fathers tell us that Miracles ceaſed, that they were unneceſſary, that to expect other then the old ones, was to tempt God.</hi> And you cite S. <hi>Chryſostom &amp; A. Operis Imperf. &amp; qq. ex Nov. Teſt.</hi> You might as well have cited S. <hi>Auſtin l. 1. de Vera Relig. c. 25. Cùm enim Eccleſia Catholica, The Catholick Church being ſpread all over the world, and founded, it was not permitted that thoſe Miracles should laſt till our days.</hi> Theſe words are as full as any you can produce, yet they do not oblige us to ſay, there were no Miracles wrought in that great Saints time. Let him explicate his own mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>l. 1. Retract. c. 14, Verum eſt quidem, That which ſaid is true; for in our days the impoſition of hands upon perſons baptized, dos not give with the Holy Ghoſt the knowledge of Languages, neither do Preachers cure the Sick with their shadow. But my words ought not ſo to be underſtood, as if no Miracles at all were done: For I my ſelf knew of a blind man cured at</hi> Milan; <hi>and ſuch like things are frequent,</hi> etiam iſtis temporibus, <hi>even in theſe dayes, that I can neither know them all, nor relate all that I know.</hi> Thus <hi>S. Auſtin.</hi> You ſee, Sir, an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſ above all exception, of not a few, but many Miracles wrought in thoſe dayes, when you pretend Miracles to have ceaſed. If we co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me nearer our Times, we shall find very many
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192171:15"/>recorded in the two <hi>S. Gregories</hi> the Great, and of <hi>Tours.</hi> And ſo on till this Age, God's hand being not now shortned, or diſabled to do them, and man's wants requiring them, chiefly to nourish in him that lively Faith in God, and hope of his help in our wants, and to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to have recourſe with confidence to the Throne of Grace. I could bring a Cloud of Witneſſes, but that in reality you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what I intend (which is another of your contradictions.)</p>
               <p>For you ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 35. That God is pleaſed to shew his Power, Juſtice, Mercy, or Divine Being, in all Ages, by ſome ſupernatural Effects. That there is no Nation, whoſe Chronicles do not teſtifie this; nay ſcarce any private man, but may obſerve ſome of theſe in himſelf. <hi>Magna Veritas &amp; praevalet.</hi> Truth forces this teſtimony from you, even when you impugne her, to shew how, <hi>Goliath</hi> like your sword is ſtill at hand, to diſpatch you. For you pretend there are no miracles in theſe later ages in the whole Church: yet you admit them, even in favour of private perſons. O, but, ſay you, theſe are not miracles, becauſe not done in Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith. Very good! at if the ſame worke, when done in Confirmation of Faith, were a miracle: if on any other Score, were none. At if you should ſay: the ſame ſeale, is tbe <hi>King's broade ſeale,</hi> when applyed to <hi>Greene wax;</hi> but is not ſuch, when it is put to <hi>Red,</hi> or <hi>yallow wax.</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:192171:15"/>Theſe are diſtinctions worthy of D. Brevint!</p>
               <p>Pag. 51. <hi>Thoſe of Chriſt, &amp; his Apoſtles were</hi> 1. <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes convenient to promote the glory of God, &amp; the good of men. 2. to confirme men in Faith. 3. Freed from all mixture with Lying wonders.</hi> Be it ſoe. Such are the miracles wrought in the Catholick Church, viz: that of <hi>Faire weather</hi> in the yeare 1675. obtained in <hi>Paris,</hi> through the interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>S. Genovef,</hi> Patroneſſe of that greate towne, which was obtained aſſoone as her Shrine was uncovered, &amp; the Prayers begun: &amp; no rayne fell till the Prayers were ended. This I mention, becauſe it is knowne to many of our nation, of both Profeſſions, &amp; even Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants owned the worke to be very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. Many likewiſe remember, that long ſince, when the King's moſt excellent Majeſty was at <hi>Paris</hi> in alike publicke neceſſity, they had recourſe to the ſame Saint for rayne, in an exceeding greate Drouth; &amp; that Rayne fell on the very day of the Proceſſion. Which of your three Conditions are wanting in theſe workes?</p>
               <p>Page 52. <hi>Moderne Roman miracles are prancks becoming Hobgoblins, &amp; fayryes.</hi> And then you fall <hi>on the viſions of our B. Lady?</hi> Which I am perſwaded no body before you ever called <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi> Soe your diſcourſe is the ſame, as if a man should ſay: <hi>Nireus</hi> was nohandſome man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Therſites</hi> was deformed. I know not whither to admire more, your <hi>Divinity,</hi> or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192171:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>your <hi>Logicke:</hi> the firſt furnishes you with the oddeſt notions, which ever entred into any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man's head: the ſecond draws them into as odde formes. Both together make you a worthy champion, of the cauſe you pleade.</p>
               <p>That ſome Spirits have appeared, is a thing ſoe cleere in both old, &amp; new Teſtament, that none, who are not ſtrangers to both can deny it. What is more cleere, then the apparitions of Angels to the Patriarck, to the Iſraelits<note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iud. 2.1.</hi>
                  </note>, to Gedeon<note n="b" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iud. 6.12.</hi>
                  </note>, to Manue &amp; his wiſe<note n="c" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iud. 13.</hi>
                  </note>, to David,<note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>2. Reg. 24.17.</hi>
                  </note> to Daniel<note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Dan. 10.</hi>
                  </note>, &amp; to Zacharias<note n="f" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Zachar. 2.1.</hi>
                  </note>. And in the new Teſtament, to another Zachary<note n="g" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luc. 1.11.</hi>
                  </note>, to our B. Lady<note n="h" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luc. 1.28.</hi>
                  </note>, to Philip the Deacon<note n="i" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Act. 8.26.</hi>
                  </note>, to S. Paul<note n="k" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Act. 27.23.</hi>
                  </note>, &amp; to S. Iohn in the Apocalypſe ſeverall times. Now if Angels appeare, why not Bleſſed Souls, <hi>Who are like Angels in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mar. 12.25.</hi>
                  </note>? S. Auſtin<note n="m" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Lib. de Cura pro mort. c. 10.</hi>
                  </note> ſays it may ſeeme <hi>Impudence</hi> to deny that ſouls appeare. And<note n="n" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ibid. c. 16.</hi>
                  </note> aſſures that he had learnt not by <hi>uncertain rumors;</hi> but by certain witneſſes, that whileſt <hi>Nola</hi> was beſiedged, <hi>S. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> appeared to many both cittizens, &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers. Now if Saints appeare, why not our B. Lady?</p>
               <p>Pag. 54. <hi>She appeared to S. Alain, who had beene a filthy companion before.</hi> What then? Chriſt appeared to <hi>S. Paul,</hi> who had beene a <hi>Perſecutor</hi> before. The change of <hi>Saul</hi> into, <hi>Paul</hi> a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192171:16"/>
                  <hi>Perſecutor</hi> into a <hi>Preacker,</hi> was a convincing argument, that it was truly <hi>Chriſt</hi> which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him. And the change of that <hi>S. Alanus</hi> proves it was a good ſpirit, which appeared to him. Now a good ſpirit could not tell a Lye, &amp; ſay he was the mother of God, without being ſoe <hi>Can ſweate grapes be gathered of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Or figs of thiſtles? Mat. 7.16.</hi> Spirits may be knowne by their fruites, as well as men.</p>
               <p>Pag. 60. <hi>Roman miracles looke another way, then thoſe of Chriſt: They are brought to prove other doctrines, then his.</hi> This is eaſily ſayd, &amp; as eaſily denyed. Your Sincerity hath not appeared ſoe greate hitherto, as that now we should take your word, &amp; grant that we have changed the Apoſtolicall Faith for a compliment, in civility, not to gain ſay you. Prove: or be ſilent.</p>
               <p>Page 66. <hi>How is this change imaginable, that shee who did not appeare in the primitive times should doe it of late? S. Auſtin as well deſerved her Protection, when he was beſieged by Barbarians, as S. Dominick.</hi> Thus you very Judiciously! As if God were always bound to give equall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings toall, who deſerve alike! Our B. Saviour deſerved as well fire from Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thoſe, who came to apprehend him, as <hi>Elias, 4. Reg. 1.10.</hi> &amp; an Army of horſes, &amp; fiery charrets, to defend him, as <hi>Elizeus, 4. Reg. 6.17.</hi> yet had them not. You have ſeene out of S. Auſtin, that <hi>S. Felix</hi> appeared at the ſiege of <hi>Nola:</hi> if the like did not happen ot Hippo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192171:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>regio, what then? Our Redeemer during his life cured many ſicke; not all, (Io. 5. we find many ſicke Lying about the sheepe pond, &amp; but one cured) he rayſed ſome to life; not all. Why not <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> as well as <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ſeing he deſerved it as well? This is a preſumptuous queſtion: it ought to ſatisfy us, that the thing being due to nether, myght be granted to ether, or refuſed without any wrong. And the will of God ought to put ſome bounds to the curioſity of man. But <hi>our B. Lady did not appeare hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> How know you, shee did not? Are all things written, which hapned? or have you reade, all that was written? or, when you writ this, did you remember all that you had read? Refresh your Memory, &amp; you will find that you have reade of an ancient Apparition of our B. Lady: you your ſelf are, my witneſſe, for p. 149. you ſay she appeared to <hi>Liberius</hi> the Pope, &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> a rich man of Rome, to order the building of <hi>S. Mary Major.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a greate misfortune, for a man to have an Itch to write, &amp; that in odious matters, who hath a ſtrong fancy, a weake Memory, little underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; no Iudgment.</hi> Examin your conſcience uppon theſe points, &amp; ſee how much of them belongs to you.</p>
               <p>I cannot omit an impious, (I might ſay Blaſphemous) hint, you make, that it is ſome bad Spirit, which appeares with the tittle of our B. Lady, or our B. Saviour. Becauſe, ſay
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192171:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, they appeare only ſince the Divil is let Looſe; not whileſt he was bound up in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times. Your old erroneous fancy workes ſtill. To correct it, know, Sir, that in the Apoſtles times, (when you fancy the Divil to have beene bound up) <hi>Satan transformed himſelf into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Lyght. (2 Cor. 11.14.)</hi> Be ashamed of your ignorance, if you did not know this: &amp; of a worſe fault, if you did know it, &amp; yet aſſert the contrary. And that it is no bad Spirit, which in later times appeares, is Evident by the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes it produces, Humility, Meekneſſe, Patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, Peace of Conſcience, a contempt of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, &amp; an eſteeme of ſpirituall things, in a word, charity to their neyghbour, &amp; a Love of God above all things, even themſelves. Theſe vertues are planted, watred, &amp; encreaſed, by theſe Apparitions in thoſe ſouls, to whome they are granted. Are theſe the fruites of a bad Spirit? Doe <hi>ſuch grapes</hi> grow on <hi>thornes?</hi> Such <hi>figs</hi> on <hi>thiſtles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But she (the ever B. Virgin) admits of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> ſay you, <hi>p.</hi> 68. She does ſoe; &amp; <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> is due to her, firſt, becauſe she is <hi>ful of Grace, (Luc. 1.28.)</hi> Secondly becauſe she is the <hi>mother of God, (Conc. Epheſ.)</hi> the hygheſt dignity any pure creature is capable of. Thirdly for the benefits we receive by her interceſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:192171:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Protection of Saints.</head>
               <p>IN your 4. Chapter having for 8. whole pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges declamed againſt our Prayers to Saints, from p. 71. to. 79. you draw at length your diſcourſe to this concluſion: <hi>The tru reaſon why praying to Saints is called Idolatry, is not becauſe they cannot heare, for this would make praying to them no more, then an Idle, &amp; uſeleſſe act: but mainly-becauſe Prayer, vows, &amp; giving of Thanks, is a main part of God's ſervice Scripture, &amp; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, ſtill reckon Prayer, &amp; Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving amongſt the truest ſacrifices, &amp; which can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to none, but God. Soe calling on them, who are not Gods, is downeryght Idolatry.</hi> Thus you. And having breathed a while you ſay: <hi>The truth is, you may call uppon a Saint, without any danger of Idolatry, if he be in ſuch a diſtance, whence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent creatures may without Miracle Heare one another.</hi> Which words deſtroy your former aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, being contradictory to it. <hi>The truth is,</hi> (if I may conjecture) when you advanced the firſt Propoſition, your Imaginative faculty had beene over heated with your forgoing diſcourſe: &amp; ſoe repreſented things amiſſe. But before you writ the following part, it had time to coole, &amp; returne to a rationall temper, &amp; then <hi>the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192171:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Truth</hi> as it <hi>is</hi> appeared, &amp; that Action, which before ſeemed <hi>Idolatry,</hi> was knowne to be <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi> Thus you condemne, &amp; abſolve us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you are diſpoſed. We are ſure God hath more conſtant meaſures, to Judge by; which is our Comfort.</p>
               <p>I will leave you to reconcile your diſagreeing thoughts, &amp; take what you grant: viz. that it is not <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to pray to Saints, provided they be not out of hearing. Moreover you ſay p. 80. <hi>It is not Idolatry to pray to your freinds by letters at what diſtance ſoever.</hi> Soe it is no <hi>Idolatry</hi> by ſetter to pray to one in the other <hi>hemiſphere.</hi> Nay you grant the ſame to a Saint in Heaven, <hi>if we have Expreſſes, to carry our letters.</hi> Which are your owne words. Soe that S. Paul, in deſiring the <hi>Romans</hi> to pray for him, had beene guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> had he not found an <hi>Expreſſe, Phebe,</hi> to carry his letter: &amp; the Prayers of Papiſts to Saints are <hi>Idolatry,</hi> becauſe they have no <hi>Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> for Heaven. Rare diſcourſe!</p>
               <p>But ſeeing the <hi>diſtance</hi> of the Saint from us, is the thing which makes Prayer to him <hi>Idolatry,</hi> shew your skill in Metaphyſick, &amp; teach us what that diſtance is: In which Scripture, &amp; fathers, as well as Divines, are ſilent. Is it a Bow's-shoote? a league? ten leagues? A Diameter of the Earth? the latitude of the whole world? The reaſon of my doubt, is becauſe Bodys have certainly a more narrow Sphere of Activity, then Spirits: yet it is not eaſy to determine the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192171:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sphere of Activity of one of our ſenſes, <hi>Seing,</hi> which diſcovers ſtars in the firmament at an unconceavable diſtance. And were there other luminous bodys ten times more remote, with a bigneſſe proportionably greater, &amp; a more vivid lyght, our Eyes would diſcerne them. Soe it is not the diſtance alone, which hinders our diſcovering ſome objects; but it is ether their obſcurity, or their poſition out of a ſtreyght Line, or their framing too little an Angle in the <hi>Retina,</hi> or the bad diſpoſition of the eye it ſelf. You ſee, Sir, it is no eaſy matter to determine the Sphere of Activity of one of our corporall ſenſes: &amp; who will then preſume to determine that of a Spirituall creature, which is much more unlimited, as drawing neerer to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, which is unlimited in all kinds? now unleſſe you can reſolve this doubt, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reover shew us at what diſtance the Saints are from us, your charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> will fall to the ground, becauſe you cannot convince, that the Saints, we pray to, be out of hearing.</p>
               <p>Whileſt you ſtudy an anſwer to this unanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werable doubt, I will teach you, what I learne out of Scripture, that the Saints doe know in Heaven what paſſes on Earth. For luke 15.7. our Saviour ſays, <hi>Ioy shall be in Heaven, over one ſinner, that repenteth.</hi> That <hi>Repentance</hi> is then <hi>knowne in Heaven,</hi> for there can be no Joy, for things unknowne. And if this, why not other things? Are there ſetled ſome <hi>Expreſſes,</hi> to carry
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192171:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>tidings, of the <hi>Repentance of a ſinner;</hi> &amp; not <hi>of the Prayers of the virtuous?</hi> Againe Abraham knew what had paſt in the times of the <hi>rich man,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lazarus:</hi> that one had <hi>received good things,</hi> the <hi>other evill things:</hi> Luke 16.25. The rich man ſaw <hi>Lazarus, Lazarus</hi> ſaw him: &amp; they ſaw their different conditions of bliſſe, &amp; miſery: &amp; they could ſpeake to one another. Soe <hi>ſouls in Limbo Patrum,</hi> as we ſay, (or as you ſay, <hi>Saints in Heaven</hi>) &amp; Damned ſouls in Hell ſee, know, &amp; converſe with one another. The rich man knew he had in the world five brethren whoſe wicked life would bring them to the Torments, he endured, if they did not amend it. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham knew the ſame, &amp; that they had <hi>Moyſes,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Prophets.</hi> How can all this ſtand, with that darke Ignorance of things of this world in which you fancy the deceaſed ſouls to live, even in Heaven? Produce your doughty argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Chriſt himſelf; ſay it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the glutton should ſee <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or ſpeake to <hi>Abraham,</hi> or <hi>Abraham</hi> reply. Alleadge Diſtance; the danger of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> &amp; what elſe you pleaſe: For all theſe things ether prove nothing againſt us, or convince our Saviour's words to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper; or worſe: Unleſſe unto your other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, you adde that of <hi>Expreſſes</hi> ſetled bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt <hi>Hell,</hi> &amp; <hi>Abraham's boſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the meanes, by which the ſouls know what paſſes here, it is not materiall: whither it be by the mediation of Angels, or Revelation,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192171:20"/>or ſeing things in the Divine Eſſence, as in <hi>a voluntary looking glaſſe,</hi> or by the force of their underſtanding, which having no dependance onſenſes, can reach to all places, or by ſeverall, or all theſe together, or by any other way unknowne to us. Each hath ſeverall good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, none is impoſſible, or improbable. But the thing is not worth the while, to examin: it belonging to <hi>Metaphyſick;</hi> not to <hi>Divinity,</hi> much leſſe to <hi>Faith.</hi> Yet it is conſiderable, that Divines find greater difficulty, to show how the ſecrets of harts are concealed from Angels, then how the reſt are made knowne to them. See <hi>S. Tho. 1. q. 55.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 81. This is to fancy in Saints an <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, if they know what paſſes in ſeverall parts of the world.</hi> My anſwer is obvious: there being ſeverall priviledges of the Divine underſtanding, not communicable to creatures. 1. that God underſtands all things poſſible, &amp; exiſtent: Saints only the later. 2. God underſtands all to come; they only what is preſent. 3. he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands by his owne eſſence; they by ſpecies. 4. his knowledge embraces all abſolutely; theirs reaches not to ſecrets of Harts. 5. His is unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitable; from theirs ſeverall things may be reſtrained when God pleaſes. 6. His is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent; theirs depends on God, without whoſe concourſe they can doe nothing. See, Sir, whither you have Metaphyſick enough, to prove <hi>that knowledge</hi> to be the <hi>Omniſcience of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192171:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>God,</hi> which is clogged: with ſoe many <hi>Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions?</hi> I would know of your Doctors, why it should not be blaſphemy to attribute to God ſuch imperfect knowledges?</p>
               <p>Page 94. You acknowledge <hi>Miracles of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaints, in the friſt three hundred yeares.</hi> Which, ſay you, <hi>tempted Chriſtians no further, them to goe, &amp; pray to God in thoſe places where they were wrought &amp; where Payers had ſometimes very extraordinary returnes: there they wisht to God, that he would heare in their behalfe, the generall Prayers, which theſe ſouls offer to God.</hi> Where you expreſſe the full ſenſe of the Prayers to Saints, in our Miſſall, &amp; Breviary. But the faith full being perſwaded, that God through the Prayers of thoſe Saints granted their requeſts, &amp; releived their wants, &amp; knowing that the Saints know what Prayers were offred up to them, why myght they not ſay, as we doe in the Lytanyes: <hi>Saint Peter pray for me?</hi> Is it not lawfull to ſay ſo, to a Saint alive in this world? &amp; why not to one living in Heaven? the reason is, ſay you, becauſe <hi>Prayer, &amp; prayſe is a ſacrifice, which no body offers to Peter, Paul, or Cyprian ſayth S. Auſtin.</hi> Doe you think what you ſay? <hi>Prayers &amp; Prayſe</hi> a ſacrifice? Can we not then without <hi>Idolatry Prayſe S Paul, or S. Peter?</hi> I cannot accuſe you of that fault: though I am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſwaded you never reprehended as Idolaters, thoſe who <hi>prayſed</hi> you, &amp; offred up that <hi>Sacrifice</hi> on your Altar. <hi>Prayer</hi> is like wiſe <hi>Idolatry!</hi> Was it Idolatry in <hi>S. Paul</hi> to Pray Saints on Earth to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192171:21"/>pray for him? why then should it be ſuch to pray Saints in Heaven to pray for us? Are they leſſe Saints? This is a myſtery, which we long have deſired to ſee revealed, &amp; long may, for you nether will, nor can explicate it.</p>
               <p>Pag. 95. <hi>Obſerve the wiles of Satan, Chriſt employes both at once his Apoſtles, &amp; his miracles, to deſtroy all Idolatry from among men: &amp; Pagans &amp; Papiſts make uſe of both, to bring it in.</hi> Unleſſe the Reader be attentive, he will think you ſpeake ſenſe; which is not tru. For tell me, I pray you, what uſe did <hi>Pagans</hi> make of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> whome they slaught erd like sheepe in the shambles? How could they uſe the Apoſtles name, which they knew not, but to hate it? Where are thoſe <hi>Pagans?</hi> what <hi>miracles</hi> do <hi>Pagans</hi> pretend to, to bring in <hi>Idolatry?</hi> what <hi>Idolatry</hi> doe <hi>Papiſts bring in?</hi> How doe they uſe the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to compaſſe that? your Period ſeemed to you full, it ſounded well in your eare: you thought it pretty, to mingle <hi>Papiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Pagans,</hi> &amp; oppoſe <hi>the wiſdome of Christ,</hi> to the <hi>wiles of Satan:</hi> ſoe you writ it downe, without regarding or exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how all could hang together, or be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed. The baſt excuſe I can find, is to lay the fault on a defect of nature. It is unreaſonable to exact <hi>a rationall diſcourſe,</hi> from one who ſeemes to want <hi>common ſenſe.</hi> He may be adviſed to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: which is the beſt counſel I can give you.</p>
               <p>But, ſay you, theſe are <hi>the words of an ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t father,</hi> &amp; cite S. <hi>Chriſoſ. hom. 1. ad Pop. Ant.</hi> In whome
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:192171:21"/>there is not one word of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the only material point to our purpoſe. Whoſe <hi>wiles</hi> are theſe, to falſify Fathers, cite theim for what they thought not of, &amp; corrupt their texts, to prove what you pleaſe? <hi>In malâ causâ non poſſunt aliter,</hi> S. Auſtin. Your bad Cauſe is capable of no better defence. I will give you your choyſe, whither S. Chriſ did, or did not mention Papiſts here? that you may the better ſee how wrechedly you entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle your ſelfe in the nets, you caſt for others, &amp; fall into the pit, you dig. Did that Saint not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Papiſts?</hi> You wrong him very much in ſaying he did. Did he ſpeake of them? they were then in the world early after Chriſt, much ſooner, then you, &amp; your brechren will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Still what you ſay is againſt yourſelfe, you carry about you your <hi>ſword.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of worship given to our B. Lady.</head>
               <p>IN your 5.6.7. &amp; 8. Chapters you very odiouſly repreſent, what hath beene ſayd, or done, to honour the ever B. Virgin, cutting the words which ſeeme harsh from others, which correct them, &amp; adding malicious gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; interpretations, to make them ſound yet more harshly. It would be tedious to reply to each particular. Soe I will deliver, what the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192171:22"/>Church profeſſes &amp; the ground of her practice, &amp; then take notice of ſome remarkable faults in your diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſteeme, Honour, Prayſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Glory,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, at their proper object, ſome perſon endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with ſome good qualitys, not in a meane; but in an excellent degree. <hi>Eſteeme</hi> is the in ward value, or reſpect we beare it. <hi>Honour</hi> is an outward expreſſion of our <hi>Eſteeme.</hi> By <hi>Prayſe</hi> we endeavour to communicate both to others: &amp; <hi>Glory</hi> is the union of many perſons in the ſame ſentiments of <hi>Eſteeme, Honour,</hi> &amp; <hi>Prayſe.</hi> It reſides not in the perſon honoured; but in the Honourer, <hi>Honor eſt in honorante;</hi> yet it takes its ſpecies from its object, which gives it its being, as all other morall habits, &amp; Acts doe.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of <hi>Honour,</hi> anſwering to two ſortes of <hi>Excellency,</hi> the one <hi>naturall,</hi> the other <hi>ſupernaturall.</hi> By <hi>naturall Excellency</hi> I underſtand all Gifts of this life, whither perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as ſcience, Art, valour, &amp;c. or Reall, as to be borne in a good country, of a noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, heyre to a greate eſtate, &amp;c. which are called goods of fortune; but are Bleſſings of God, not depending on any induſtry, and therefore are diſtinguisht from perſonall endow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments. By <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> I underſtand all gifts exceeding the force of nature, which leade men to their firſt principle, &amp; laſt end, God: viz, <hi>Grace,</hi> &amp; <hi>Glory:</hi> all ſupernurall vertues
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192171:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Theologicall, or morall. Item, thoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which God uſes for our ſanctification: as the <hi>Bible, Sacraments, Churchs, ſacred veſſells, &amp; veſtments, Perſons Conſecrated to God:</hi> item <hi>Saints Bodys,</hi> as having beene Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; living members of Chriſt. There is athird kind of Excellency which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of both theſe, it being a meane bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt them: viz that of Kings, which is called <hi>Sacred,</hi> as coming from God (<hi>Prov. 8.15. Rom. 13.1. &amp; 1. Pet. 2.13.</hi>) Yet it partakes ſomething of the other Excellency, becauſe God uſed the wills of men to eſtablish it. This worship ſtops not in the perſon of the Monarck; but ſpreades from him to all employed by him, (<hi>1. Pet. 2.13.</hi>) even to the meaneſt, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to the authority communicated to them. This <hi>worship</hi> we call <hi>Civill:</hi> that of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall things, is called <hi>Religious:</hi> that of naturall may be called <hi>Merall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God, containing within himſelf all Perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which can move eſteeme in amoſt Eminent degree, being the fountaine of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Goodneſſe, &amp; all ſupernaturall gifts, the ſupreame Lord of all Creatures, &amp; King even of Kings, is the Prime object of <hi>worship,</hi> of <hi>Adoration,</hi> of <hi>Prayſe</hi> of all Creatures in all kinds. The ſplendor of the Sun is darkneſſe, the riches of the Earth, Poverty, the wiſedome of the wiſeſt, folly, the power of the Myghty, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe, the Majeſty of Kings, contemptible, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192171:23"/>Juſtice of the Ryghteous, as <hi>filthy rags</hi> (<hi>quaſi pannus menſtruatae, Iſa. 64.6.</hi>) if compared with the Lyght, Riches, wiſdome, Power, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, &amp; Juſtice of God. The Iſlands compared to his greatneſſe, are like duſt: &amp; the whole world <hi>a drop of a Bucket, gutta ſitulae, Iſa. 40.15.</hi> All creatures are as if they had no being, when ſet before that Eſſentiall Being <hi>Eſſe per Eſſentiam.</hi> Hence no Prayſe, no Honour can equall him. <hi>Quantum potes, tantum aude, quia major omni lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, neclaudare ſufficis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is an undeniable truth, which yet is abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to eſtablish two pernitious Errours. For hence Proteſtans deny, that any Religious cult is due Saints: &amp; our later ſectaryes, their breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, refuſe all Civill worship to Magiſtrates. Both alleadge that ſaying. <hi>Soli Deo: to God alone Honour &amp; Glory,</hi> not minding, that the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Rome 13.7.</hi> commands us <hi>to render to all their due, Honour, to whome honour,</hi> &amp; <hi>S.</hi> Peter teaches us firſt <hi>to feare God,</hi> next <hi>to Honour the King. 1. Pet. 2.17.</hi> which places may ſtop the mouths of ſectarys, shewing an honour due to Kings: it may likewiſe open the eyes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, shewing an eſteeme due to ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall gifts. Nay their owne practice convinces their errour: ſeing they shew ſome more reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the <hi>Bible,</hi> then to a <hi>Romance;</hi> to a Church then to an Alehouſe; to a Saint, then to a theife; to <hi>S. Paul,</hi> then to <hi>Iudas.</hi> And call this reſpect as you pleaſe, we call it <hi>Religious,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192171:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>the diſpute about that name, will be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: In which we have the advantage becauſe our worship of Saints ends not in them; but in God, who is <hi>admirable in them:</hi> as all Civill worship ends not in the ſubordinate officers of ſtate; but in Kings, for whoſe ſake alone others are reſpected, &amp; obeyed.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing then ſome Honour due to Saints, as they partake of God's goodneſſe we shall find ground enough for the like, &amp; greater in the <hi>Mother of God.</hi> The Angel called her <hi>full of Grace (Luke 1.21.)</hi> she was ſayd to <hi>bleſt amongſt all women (ibid. v. 42.)</hi> &amp; she by divine inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion foreſaw she should be called <hi>Bleſſed by all Generations,</hi> by reaſon of the manifold gifts of the H. Gheſt. No doubt but that Grace, with which the Angel found her, was much encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a perpetuall practice of vertu. Her Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in ſtiling her ſelf the <hi>hand may de of God,</hi> when she was called to be his <hi>mother</hi> was of ſoe greate merit, that its quantity without temeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot be determined.</p>
               <p>It is her ſingular prerogative, to be the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God.</hi> Her fullneſſe of Grace rayſed her above all men: this rayſes her above all Saints and Angels, none being ſoe related to God. Wherefore a greater honour is due to her, then to them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore there is an honour due to Saints, to the mother of God, &amp; to God: which being different, are expreſt by different words, that of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192171:24"/>Saints we call <hi>Douleia,</hi> that of ouw B. Lady. <hi>Hyperdouleia:</hi> &amp; that of God <hi>Latreia.</hi> The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne reformers dislike theſe words, for their Etymologye: but their doubt is not worth the anſwering, ſeing uſe &amp; cuſtome gives, or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the ſignification of words.</p>
               <p>But ſay you pag 101. She is called a <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe.</hi> Anſ. it may be, as God is ſayd (<hi>pſal. 82.1.) to Iudge the Gods.</hi> And againe: <hi>I have ſayd: you are Gods. Now if he called them Gods to whome the word of God Came</hi> (John 10.35.) why not our B. Lady, in alike ſenſe, to whome the tru eternall word came, &amp; dwelt in her? This you wil ſay is only a metaphorical Divinity; &amp; I ſay ſo too; &amp; I anathematize any, who shall ſay, she is a Goddeſſe properly. But the ground of this calumny is very childish, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, forſooth, she is called <hi>Diva:</hi> which title every Grammarian knows, to be given to all Saints, &amp; uſed promiſcuouſly with <hi>Beata,</hi> or <hi>Sancta.</hi> In the Civill Law you may find it given promiſcuouſly to all Emperours, even Pagans: whome no Chriſtian ever thought to be Gods.</p>
               <p>Pag. 142. <hi>We keepe, ſay you, holy days to her Honour:</hi> a thing due only to God. Anſ. we doe So. And you keepe Holy-days to the honour of the Apoſtles: &amp; why this, if Holy-days be due only to God? your ſword is never moved, but to your prejudice, it never ſtrikes at us, but through your owne ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192171:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Satisfactions, &amp; Indulgences.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN your 9. Chapter you declame againſt the treaſure of the Roman Church: &amp; in your 10. againſt Indulgences. Which having greate affinity, I will treate them together. I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with an explication of the doctrine, which the Church oblidges her children to beleive, &amp; as for other points, as she doth, ſoe will I leave their diſcuſſion to Divines, whoſe opinions they are, rather then Doctrine of Faith. And that my Explication of Faith in theſe points may be more authenticall, I will deliver it in the words of a worthy Prelate the Bishop of Condom, Preceptor to the Dolphin, publisht lately in our language.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not only Iuſt; but beneficiall unto us, <hi>ſays he,</hi> that God forgiving us the ſin, &amp; remitting us the eternall punishment, we have incurred, should impoſe ſome temporall penalty, to retaine us within our dutyes, leaſt being delivered too ſoone from the bonds of his Iuſtice, we should aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>donour ſelves unto a temerarious Conſidence, abuſing the facility of his Indulgence.</p>
               <p>It is therefore in order to our diſcharging that obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that we are ſubjected to ſome workes of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which we are bound to performe in the Spirit
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:192171:25"/>of Humility, &amp; Repentance: &amp; the neceſſity of theſe ſatisfactory workes was the motive, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Primitive Church, to impoſe uppon Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thoſe Pennances called Canonicall.</p>
               <p>See that when the Church inflicts uppon ſinners Painfull, &amp; laborious injunctions, &amp; they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them with Humility, that act we call ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: &amp; when ether in regard of the Zeale, &amp; fervour of the Penitent, or other good work perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which the Church hath preſcribed, she relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſome part of the Pennance, which was Owing, this remiſſion is called Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The Council of Trent propoſeth no more to our Faith in the point of Indulgences, then this, that the power of granting them hath beene given the Church by Chriſt Ieſus: &amp; that the uſe of them is beneficiall. Where unto the Council addeth: that the grant of them ought to be diſpenced with caution, least the Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline should be weakened, &amp; enervated by an exceſſive facility, which advice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth that the manner of diſpoſing of Indulgences appartaineth to church diſcipline. <hi>Thus far out of this greate perſon. What have you to ſay againſt this Catholick doctrine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You employ one &amp; fifty pages declaming againſt this Treaſure, &amp; theſe Indulgences: viz from the 189. till the 240. yet in the midſt of all this tranſport, we find a</hi> lucid intervall, <hi>where Truth (againſt which in the reſt you diſcourſe) forces you to depoſe in her favour. For pag. 216. I find theſe words:</hi> It was the practice of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192171:25"/>Holy Church to expell from their ſociety ſcandalous, &amp; knowne ſinners. They were enjoyned to pray, to faſt, to curb, &amp; to mortify their flesh, to afflict their ſouls for their ſins, &amp; to apply themſelves to all ſuch workes, as myght both improve, &amp; declare their in ward ſincere Repentance. Theſe long, &amp; holy exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did paſſe among all Chriſtians, for <hi>SATISFAC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS</hi> to the Church, &amp; in ſome manner to God too. Before the Church moſt properly, becauſe that was all which Church diſcipline required: &amp; before God in a lower, yet a very tru, &amp; proper ſenſe: becauſe it is the main condition, which God requires of Offenders which he is in his mercy both ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, &amp; pleaſed with, when they Sincerely performe it. They were to doe it alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g while, ſome a whole yeare, ſome two, ſome ten, ſome according to the enormity of the ſin, all their life long. <hi>Thus you, of ſatisfaction by Penitentiall workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 218. You continu your explication of this matter.</hi> There now and then hapned, <hi>ſay you ſuch cauſes, as</hi> moved them <hi>(the Bishops)</hi> to be more free, <hi>by shortning the time of ſinners Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:</hi> As when the ſinner gave ſignall proofes, of an extraordinary ſorrow: when he ſtoutly owned, &amp; defended the Chriſtian Faith, when in times of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, they were to be ſtrengthned to Martyr dome: when valiant Confeſſors did interceede for ſome of their freinds: on theſe, &amp; other like rationall, &amp; pious Inducements, the holy Fathers thought they myght ether eaſe ſuch Penitents of the length, or ſome times quite diſcharge them of the whole bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192171:26"/>then. And this Relaxation of Eccleſiasticall Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſome Latin Fathers (Tertullian, &amp; S. Cyprian) call in their writings by the name of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here you ſoe exactly agree with what I have written out of our Bishop de Condom, that you may ſeeme to have copyed him, or both to have taken your ſentiments out of ſome third.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At leaſt this is evident, that you owne as much as that Authour teacheth to be the Faith of the Roman Catholick Church, &amp; conſequently your Cenſure on our Faith in theſe points of</hi> ſatisfaction even to God, <hi>&amp;</hi> Indulgences, <hi>is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of your ſelf.</hi> Magna veritas, &amp; praevalet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Confraternityes.</head>
               <p>CHapter 11. you traduce our Confraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, c. 12. you play with the girdle of S. Francis. c. 13. you deride the Scapulary of S. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stock &amp;c. 14. make your ſelfe merry with the Roſary. All which being no points of our <hi>Faith,</hi> I do not think my ſelfe oblidged to aſſert them in this pamphlet. Yet I will tell you, what you know already, though you Slily inſinuate the contrary pag. 300. that we preach <hi>Faith, Repentance, Perſeverance in well doing &amp;c.</hi> more
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192171:26"/>then Proteſtants: ſeing we hold them abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely neceſſary to ſalvation, <hi>Faith without workes being dead,</hi> as we teach with S. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes; &amp; you teach Faith alone to Juſtify: we exhort People to them with hopes of a reward, they being meritorious; &amp; you deny all merits.</p>
               <p>We uſe, indead, thoſe things you ſpeake of, as helpes of our Faith, exerciſes of our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; meanes to ſtrengthen our frailty to Perſever in well-doing. It is a Calumny, to ſay, we think <hi>Faith, Hope, &amp; Charity</hi> unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or, that we teach, any can be ſaved without them, even when we invite men to theſe <hi>Gilds,</hi> or Confraternitys, into which men enter only with intention to encreaſe thoſe vertues in their ſouls. We feele, we know, we owne our inclination to Evill from our Infancy, we are convinced, that our Will, of it ſelf is inſenſible, nay ſtupid, as to all Good: that words have little force uppon it, but that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are much more powerfull. Hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares the firſt advantage of thoſe, who are incorporated into thoſe Congregations, which conſiſt of men, who <hi>forgetting thoſe things. which are behind, &amp; reaching forth unto thoſe things. which are before, preſſe towards the marke.</hi> Philip. 3. ſuch men, <hi>who conſider one another, to provoke to love, &amp; good workes,</hi> Heb. 10.24. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Confraternity of <hi>Charity,</hi> begun by <hi>P. Vincent de Paul:</hi> which with the Almes it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192171:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>gathered, releived all the poore of <hi>Loraine, Champagne, &amp; Picardie,</hi> many Ladys of the beſt quality after entring into that Congregation, turned to the releife of the poore, what before they ſpent on vanity, or loſt by gaming: &amp; changed their chambers, &amp; Cloſets, into well ſtored wardrobes filled with ſutes of Clothes of all bigneſſes, for both ſexes, which they beſtowed uppon the naked Poore, in whoſe perſons they they were taught to conſider Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>Another advantage is, that our Prayers are more efficacious when offred in company, then when ſingle. All the vertu of our Prayers is derived from that of our B. Saviour now he aſſures us, <hi>that where two, are aſſembled in his name, he is there in the midſt of them.</hi> (<hi>Mat 18.20.</hi>) And he aſſiſts there, not as an Idle ſpectator, (as many Proteſtants goe to Church, to ſee, &amp; be ſeene;) but to enlyghten the mind of the perſons aſſembled with divine inſpirations, to enflame their Will, with the love of God, &amp; their neyghbour: To incite them to Pray; to repreſent their Prayers to his Heavenly Father, &amp; ſecond them with his owne: to powre into their harts the Bleſſings he obtaines, through the merit of thoſe Wounds, he once endured for our Redemption, &amp; ever ſince retaines, to shew them to God the Father, <hi>in whoſe preſence be appeares for us.</hi> Theſe are the deſignes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternitys.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:192171:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>We know, Sir, that the <hi>Honour of God,</hi> &amp; <hi>tru Religion</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> &amp; <hi>Charity.</hi> Theſe are nourisht by the Concourſe of many Perſons to encreaſe theſe interiour vertues, by exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour exerciſes of Piety, &amp; Mortification. To call theſe together the <hi>Roſary, Scapular,</hi> &amp; Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle are uſed, with <hi>Indulgences,</hi> to make the call more efficacious. Now whither is more to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, we, for uſing theſe helpes, or you for reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Images.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur 16. Chapter is ſpent in declaming againſt our <hi>Images:</hi> which ſome other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perſons having in hand, I wil leave to them, leaſt I myght ſeeme to thruſt my ſickle into others harveſt. Probably I may shortly have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to treate of it at large, on my owne Score: &amp; there I hope to convince the unjuſtice of the charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> put up againſt our Church. For the preſent I will only take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſome greate untruths, peculiar to your ſelf.</p>
               <p>Pag. 332. <hi>This Experience is moſt certain, that, the People of God excepted, all the world beſides hath bindrawne to their reſpective Religions by the help of theſe groſſ Images.</hi> Anſwer: this
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:192171:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>is <hi>a moſt certain untruth,</hi> as appeares by the Turkes, who have none: &amp; if we beleive <hi>Varro,</hi> the Romans were a long time with out any.</p>
               <p>Pag. 337. <hi>The main motive, which drives Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims to thoſe Churches, where Images are, is to find, not the Reſemblance, but the very preſence of the Saint.</hi> This is untru: we nether beleive, nor teach any ſuch thing, nay we teach the quite contrary, as you may ſee in all our <hi>Catechiſmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pag. 402. <hi>I do not love,</hi> ſay you, <hi>to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate burthens, which of themſelves are too heavy: but without aggravation, it is moſt certain, that the Roman Church ſerves more Images, then all the Heathens did together.</hi> You could not have found a fitter concluſion of your booke, then this. At leaſt you have obſerved that Rule of the Poet:
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— Servetur ad imum</l>
                        <l>Qualis ab inceptoproceſſerit, &amp; ſibi conſtet.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>For the ſame Spirit of falshood runs through all. You began with an untruh, as I have shewed: I have likewiſe taken notice of many untruths all along, <hi>&amp; without aggravation,</hi> what you ſay here, is as greate, &amp; as evident an untruth, as ever was ſpoken in matter of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane hyſtory. It is impoſſible to reckon up all the Gods, which the Pagans adored, when (beſides dead men) beaſts, fishes, fowle, &amp; Elements, were adored: when every Plant, &amp;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192171:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tree was thought ammated with a Divinity. What ſay I, <hi>one?</hi> Each Plant had many. For Corne alone <hi>S. Aug. (l. 4. de Civ. Dei cap. 8.)</hi> reckons up twelve, (&amp; yet he profeſſes he reckons not all) viz, <hi>Seia, Segetia, Tutilina, Proſerpina, Nodotus, Volutina, Patelena, Hostili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Flora, Lacturcia, Matuta,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rumina.</hi> In the ſame place, he ſays, that one Porter, (one man) is ſufficient to keepe one dore; &amp; the Pagans put three Gods to each dore, viz, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus, Cardea,</hi> &amp; <hi>Limentinus.</hi> And as if theſe were not ſufficient: on ſome occaſions three more are added to them, (when a woman was delivered) to wit, <hi>Intercidona, Pilumnus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Deverra,</hi> to keepe out <hi>Silvanus,</hi> a dangerous God. This as alſo four Gods for every marriage, <hi>Iugatinus, Domiducus, Domitius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> Item ſix, others, who Preſide in the nuptiall bed, with their names, &amp; offices, you may ſee in <hi>S. Aug. l. 6. de Civ. Dei c. 9.</hi> And should I reckon up all the Gods who ſucceede one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the care of every man from <hi>Iugatinus,</hi> till he be brought before, <hi>Minos, Aeacus</hi> &amp; <hi>Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damanthus,</hi> and to the Elyſian feilds, I should ſpend more paper, then in all this pamphlet, now if the Romans, &amp; Grecians had ſuch a numberleſſe number of Gods, who can give account of all the Gods, of other Pagans, all over the world?</p>
               <p>If notwithſtanding all this, you ſtill think your aſſertion tru, &amp; that <hi>without aggravation,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192171:29"/>Papiſts,</hi> adore more <hi>Images,</hi> then <hi>Pagans</hi> had <hi>Gods,</hi> I shall think your <hi>Arithmetick</hi> equall to your <hi>Logick,</hi> &amp; <hi>Divinity:</hi> &amp; that you neede more, to be Prayed for, then Diſputed againſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>THe deſire of appearing in the world with the title of an <hi>Authour,</hi> to be ſpoken of, with applauſe, &amp; Prayſe, to be pointed at in the ſtreetes, to heare, as you walke that whisper: <hi>this is that Demoſtenes, that is M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.</hi> This deſire I ſay, is very violent, becauſe it ſymbolizes with that vanity, whereof the ſeedes were caſt into our ſouls by the ſin of our firſt Parents. A ſcholler thinks his beſt yeares ill ſpent in ſtudyes, unleſſe the world be partaker of his knowledge. A <hi>knowing ſilence,</hi> is no more eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or regarded, then an <hi>Ignorant ſilence.</hi> In many the Pleaſure of knowing doth not conſiſt in Conceiving, ſo much as in Producing: &amp; they looſe all the ſatisfaction they tooke in it, if the world doth not know, that they are learned.</p>
               <p>This Paſſion is ſtrengthned by another, of cenſuring what is above us, even the moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime in the world. Our Pride is pleaſed with an Imaginary Elevation above thoſe, whome we preſume to Judge, &amp; with taking a ſoveraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192171:29"/>authority over thoſe, whome we ſubmit to the Rules of our Critick. Hence no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by troubles a <hi>Cobler,</hi> or <hi>Tinker,</hi> with cenſures of their worke; &amp; there is none who doth not preſume to cenſure both <hi>Prelate,</hi> &amp; <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think no body will Judge me rash, if I ſay ſome of theſe shings concurred, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve you to appeare in Print. No body attacked you, you myght have enioyed your Benefice, and other contentments of this life in Peace. But you deſired to shew the world, by ſome worke of your owne, that you had ſpent your time well. And to doe this with more noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, you choſe for the ſubject of your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings <hi>Maſſe,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Roman Church:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the later is (even by Confeſſion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) the moſt Illuſtrious part of the Church of Chriſt; &amp; as we ſay, &amp; prove, is <hi>the tru Catholicke, &amp; Apoſtolicall Church.</hi> The other is the prime part of her Divine worship, to which all her other Religious Actions are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
               <p>This is a greate Ambirion, to ſubmit <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> to your Cenſure, to rayſe a throne above the Hygheſt on Earth, &amp; to Judge the firſt ſeate, which according to ancient Canons, is Judged by none: <hi>Prima ſedes à nemine judicatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This vaine preſumption, &amp; ambition is unexcuſable. Yet it may ſeeme modeſt, if
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192171:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>compared with your vanity, in thinking, that all the world, convinced with your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſubmittes to your Cenſures, &amp; ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes to your verdict, only becauſe they doe not reply: Although ſilence is as well, &amp; as often an effect of neglect, of contempt, or disdaine, as of conſent, &amp; approbation. But your heade is ſo full, humble man! of an eſteeme of your owne perfections, that you cannot ſurmiſe any one can have any other ſentiments, but of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for your adored ſelfe, Hence very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in the Preface to this booke, you ſay, That you had layd <hi>maſſe in the Dirt.</hi> And as if this were not low enough: pag. 407. you ſay, you have <hi>confounded maſſe even to Hell.</hi> Go further with the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or <hi>Talmud,</hi> who can. This is a <hi>non plus ultra</hi> of Inſolency, &amp; all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſons will take it for a convincing prooſe of your vanity, Ignorance &amp; weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, that if only throwing dirt, with or without cauſe, could doe the deede, you have layd both <hi>Popery</hi> &amp; <hi>maſſe</hi> in the dirt, for you have throwne it liberally. But Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Nature, unleſſe their Truth be manifeſt, reflect on the Accuſer, in this Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, and learned age: &amp; I am perſwaded, that the greateſt part of the world think the dirt, you with ſoe much labour gathered together, to throw at <hi>maſſe,</hi> lyes cloſe about you, &amp; ſtickes ſtill to your owne hands, from which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192171:30"/>it cannot be washt, but by Retracting your calumnyes.</p>
               <p>I have ſayd enough to your <hi>Saul &amp; Samuel at Endor,</hi> to shew, that though your Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſtrong yet your Reaſons are weake, &amp; your Diſcourſe incoherent: And that you imitate Goliah, you your ſelfe doe furnish armes enough to confute you, by your owne Contradictions, the fowleſt fault any ſcholler can be guilty of. By this <hi>claw,</hi> I gueſſe what a <hi>Lion</hi> you are, &amp; can frame an Idea of what you ſay againſt maſſe, althô I never reade your booke concerning it. It may be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you may heare more from me about it, if an occaſion preſent it ſelfe, &amp; the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it.</p>
               <p>In the interim learne to have ſome reſpect for your Readers; preſume not ſo much uppon your empty title of D. D. as to think to ſtun us with lowd clamours, &amp; that your words (though voyde of ſenſe) should be taken as Oracles. If you continu your reſolution to write againſt us, weygh well what you ſay, ſay nothing without a good Prooſe, and expreſſe all with the Modeſty, &amp; Gravity, beſeeming the ſubject you treate, &amp; the character you beare: And your worke shall not be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOURS E. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:31"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 8. <hi>l.</hi> 18. in the title. pag. 15. <hi>l.</hi> 25. know. <hi>Reade</hi> knowne. Pag. 25. <hi>l.</hi> 7. ut. <hi>R.</hi> up. Pag. 28. <hi>l.</hi> 26. at if. <hi>R.</hi> as if. <hi>Ibid. l.</hi> 28. at. <hi>R.</hi> as. Pag. 30. <hi>l.</hi> 10. Patriark. <hi>R.</hi> Patriarks. Pag. 31. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Priacker. <hi>R.</hi> Preacher. Pag. 32. <hi>l.</hi> 30. tittle. <hi>R.</hi> title. Pag. 39. <hi>l.</hi> 6. friſt. <hi>R.</hi> firſt. Pag. 41. <hi>l.</hi> 5. brechren. <hi>R.</hi> brethren. Pag. 42. <hi>l.</hi> 5. at. <hi>R.</hi> as. <hi>Ibid. l. ult.</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurall. <hi>R.</hi> ſupernaturall. Pag. 45. <hi>l.</hi> 16. Gheſt. <hi>R.</hi> Ghoſt. Pag. 46. <hi>l.</hi> 1. ouw. <hi>R.</hi> our. Pag. 47. <hi>l.</hi> 14. ately. <hi>R.</hi> lately.</p>
            <p>At the end of the lines very many ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles through the whole worke are divided: which altring not the ſenſe, I leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrected.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:192171:31"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
